<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The narrative of Lawrence Mowbray of Leeds, in the county of York, Gent., concerning the bloody popish conspiracy against the life of His Sacred Majesty, the government, and the Protestant religion wherein is contained I. His knowledge of the said design, from the very first in the year 1676, with the opportunity he had to be acquainted therewith, ... II. How far Sir Thomas Gascoigne, Sir Miles Stapleton, &amp;c. are engaged in the design of killing the King and firing the cities of London and York, for the more speedy setting uppermost the popish religion in England, III. An account of the assemblings of many popish priests and Jesuits at Father Rishton's Chamber ..., IV. The discovery of the erecting a nunnery at Dolebank in Yorkshire ..., V. A manifestation of the papists fraudulent conveying of their estates, himself being privy to some of them, VI. A probable opinion concerning the Jesuits, the grand instruments in these affairs : together with an account of the endeavours that were used to stifle his evidence, by making an attempt upon his life in Leicester-Fields.</title>
            <author>Mowbray, Lawrence.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10191</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13111694</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13111694</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97685</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97685)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 746:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The narrative of Lawrence Mowbray of Leeds, in the county of York, Gent., concerning the bloody popish conspiracy against the life of His Sacred Majesty, the government, and the Protestant religion wherein is contained I. His knowledge of the said design, from the very first in the year 1676, with the opportunity he had to be acquainted therewith, ... II. How far Sir Thomas Gascoigne, Sir Miles Stapleton, &amp;c. are engaged in the design of killing the King and firing the cities of London and York, for the more speedy setting uppermost the popish religion in England, III. An account of the assemblings of many popish priests and Jesuits at Father Rishton's Chamber ..., IV. The discovery of the erecting a nunnery at Dolebank in Yorkshire ..., V. A manifestation of the papists fraudulent conveying of their estates, himself being privy to some of them, VI. A probable opinion concerning the Jesuits, the grand instruments in these affairs : together with an account of the endeavours that were used to stifle his evidence, by making an attempt upon his life in Leicester-Fields.</title>
                  <author>Mowbray, Lawrence.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 [i.e. 35] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ..., and Jacob Sampson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:97685:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>February</hi> the 5th. 1679/80</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>I Do appoint <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> and <hi>Jacob Sampſon</hi> to Print this my <hi>Narrative,</hi> and that no other Print the ſame, nor any part of it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Lawr. Mowbray.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97685:1"/>
            <p>THE NARRATIVE OF Lawrence Mowbray Of LEEDS, In the County of YORK, Gent.</p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Bloody Popiſh Conſpiarcy</hi> againſt the Life of His Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty, the Government, and the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>Wherein is Contained</p>
            <p n="1">I. His <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Deſign,</hi> from the very firſt in the year 1676. with the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity he had to be acquainted therewith; and the <hi>Reaſons</hi> why he concealed it ſo long; with the manner of his diſcovering the ſaid <hi>wicked Project</hi> to His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and His moſt <hi>Honourable Privy Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. How far Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne,</hi> Sir <hi>Miles Stapleton,</hi> &amp;c. are engaged in the <hi>deſign</hi> of <hi>Killing</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Firing</hi> the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> for the more ſpeedy ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting uppermoſt the <hi>Popiſh Religion</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. An Account of the Aſſemblings of many <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> at Father <hi>Riſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Chamber, at Sir <hi>Tho. Gaſcoigne</hi>'s Houſe at <hi>Barmebow,</hi> with their <hi>Conſultations</hi> and <hi>Determinations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. A <hi>Diſcovery</hi> of the Erecting a <hi>Nunnery</hi> at <hi>Dolebank</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> by the <hi>Popiſh Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> eſpecially by Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne,</hi> with an Account of an Eſtate of ninety pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> ſettled thereupon by him.</p>
            <p n="5">V. A Manifeſtation of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> fraudulent conveying of their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> himſelf being privy to ſome of them.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. A probable opinion concerning the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> the grand Inſtruments in theſe Affairs.</p>
            <p>With other <hi>Conſiderable Matters</hi> relating to the <hi>Plot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with an Account of the Endeavours that were uſed to ſtifle his <hi>Evidence,</hi> by making an Attempt upon his <hi>Life</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter-Fields.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the <hi>Princes Arms,</hi> and <hi>Jacob Sampſon,</hi> next door to the <hi>Wonder-Tavern</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-Street.</hi> MDCLXXX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97685:2"/>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:97685:2"/>
               <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>Heneage,</hi> Lord <hi>Finch,</hi> Baron of <hi>Daventry,</hi> Lord High Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> and One of His Majesties most Honourable Privy-Council.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Dare not permit the enſuing <hi>Papers</hi> to approach your <hi>Lordſhips preſence</hi> without an <hi>Apology;</hi> For had not your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> afforded ſome ſignal <hi>Encouragement</hi> to the poor <hi>Author,</hi> nothing of <hi>This</hi> had preſumed to interrupt your <hi>Lordſhips great Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Cares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet the <hi>ſubject</hi> matter herein contained (beſides your particular <hi>Favours</hi> afforded to my ſelf) which I hope (at leaſt in my deſires and deſign) is <hi>contributory</hi> to the <hi>prevention</hi> of eminent dangers to <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> may plead my <hi>excuſe,</hi> as not unworthy of your <hi>Lordſhips Conſideration,</hi> who is ſo great a <hi>Lover</hi> of <hi>them both,</hi> and hath ſo immediate a <hi>concern</hi> in their <hi>preſervation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I had the Pen of a <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> or a <hi>Cicero,</hi> or (to ſum them up both in <hi>one) your own,</hi> I might then have adventured to <hi>enlarge</hi> on the <hi>Theme</hi> of your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Merit, which is able to <hi>inſpirit</hi> the moſt <hi>jejune</hi> and barren Orator; but in regard it <hi>Tranſcends</hi> the ſmall <hi>pittance</hi> of my <hi>diſuſed skill,</hi> I ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be <hi>ſilent</hi> than ſpeak <hi>too little</hi> of <hi>what</hi> I am never able to ſpeak <hi>enough.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have read in our <hi>Chronicles</hi> concerning Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that never any <hi>Prince</hi> who ſwayed the <hi>Engliſh Scepter</hi> had more <hi>ſapient</hi> and <hi>vigilant Councellors</hi> than <hi>Her Majeſty.</hi> Amongſt whom I have heard it reported of Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham, Secretary</hi> of <hi>State</hi> in <hi>Queen Elizabeths</hi> time, that he was ſo prudently watchful over the <hi>deſigns</hi> of the <hi>Popiſh Emiſſaries and Prieſts,</hi> that he maintained divers private <hi>Agents</hi> for that purpoſe in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, who did ſo <hi>cunningly</hi> and <hi>diſſembling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> carry the matter, that the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, <hi>in ſuae infallibilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis opprobrium,</hi> paid <hi>Penſions</hi> to ſome of thoſe <hi>Setters,</hi> who probably <hi>pretended</hi> to do ſervice on both ſides; for no ſuch <hi>Key</hi> to unlock the <hi>Apoſtolical Chamber,</hi> nay, the very <hi>Conclave,</hi> as
<pb facs="tcp:97685:3"/>
a <hi>diſguiſed</hi> (yet fugitive) <hi>Privado.</hi> It cannot be denied but <hi>thoſe</hi> days were very <hi>critical,</hi> when <hi>Parry, Squire,</hi> &amp;c. were <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borned,</hi> and <hi>encouraged</hi> by the <hi>Jeſuited party</hi> to Murther that <hi>Queen;</hi> and upon that account extraordinary <hi>diligence</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> to <hi>prevent</hi> any <hi>inconvenience,</hi> which, by the <hi>policy</hi> of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> might accrue, to their <hi>Queen, Lady,</hi> and <hi>Miſtreſs.</hi> And herein <hi>ſhe</hi> was as <hi>happy</hi> in her <hi>Servants,</hi> as <hi>they</hi> were <hi>proſperous</hi> in their <hi>ſucceſs,</hi> leaving <hi>her</hi> to expire in a <hi>good old age,</hi> as a <hi>fruit</hi> of <hi>their vigilance</hi> and <hi>care,</hi> next to <hi>Gods</hi> bleſſing and <hi>protection</hi> over her.</p>
               <p>I know <hi>our</hi> times are as deſigning as <hi>theirs,</hi> and the means uſed to accompliſh their purpoſe of deſtroying our <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> is ſuitable to what <hi>methods</hi> were then put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, either by <hi>Poyſon, Aſſaſſination,</hi> or the like. And therefore it is <hi>Gods</hi> goodneſs to our <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> to raiſe up many <hi>Walſinghams,</hi> I mean <hi>Honourable</hi> and <hi>Faithful Councellors,</hi> who watch night and day for the preſervation of His <hi>Majeſties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> amongſt us.</p>
               <p>Amongſt <hi>theſe,</hi> your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> is placed in the higheſt <hi>Orb,</hi> and that not by a <hi>caſual</hi> frolick (by which yet ſome are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced) of blind <hi>Favour,</hi> but by a <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>acknowledged de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert,</hi> after ſeveral <hi>remarkable</hi> Gradations of <hi>Dignities</hi> and <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> which were but <hi>praevious</hi> to that <hi>Eminency</hi> wherewith your Lordſhip now <hi>ſhines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is therefore the <hi>happineſs</hi> of His <hi>Majeſty</hi> to be ſo <hi>ſerved</hi> and <hi>ſecured;</hi> and not <hi>his</hi> alone, but all <hi>thoſe</hi> concerned in the <hi>diſcovery</hi> of this <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>helliſh Deſign,</hi> have reaſon to bleſs <hi>God</hi> for the acknowledged <hi>protection</hi> and <hi>encouragement</hi> which <hi>you</hi> are pleaſed to afford <hi>them,</hi> and in particular to <hi>my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Tribute</hi> I am to pay your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> is only my <hi>humble acknowledgment (more</hi> I cannot, <hi>leſs</hi> I may not); the ſame, which <hi>God</hi> is pleaſed to accept from thankful <hi>ſupplicants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I had it <hi>firſt</hi> in my thoughts to have made my <hi>Epiſtolary Addreſs</hi> to His <hi>Majeſty himſelf;</hi> and I was <hi>encouraged</hi> thereunto by ſome <hi>Inſtances,</hi> wherein <hi>mean perſons</hi> have addreſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto great <hi>Potentates</hi> to forewarn them of their <hi>dangers.</hi> I ſhall only cite <hi>two Examples,</hi> both being of our <hi>Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors;</hi> one ſitting on the <hi>Scotiſh,</hi> another on the <hi>Engliſh Throne,</hi> both which are now happily united in the <hi>perſon</hi> of our <hi>Royal Soveraign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb facs="tcp:97685:3"/>1. When King <hi>James</hi> the 4th of <hi>Scotland</hi> was preparing his <hi>Army</hi> to fight againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in the battel of <hi>Floddin,</hi> being in the midſt of his <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Collonels</hi> at prayer, <hi>a Grave ancient Country-man</hi> preſſed in through the <hi>crowd</hi> to the <hi>Kings</hi> Chair, and <hi>leaning</hi> familiarly thereon, told him, <hi>That he and his followers ſhould not proſper in that War, and therefore he wiſhed him to deſiſt,</hi> Buchan. Hiſt. Scot. lib. 13. The <hi>King</hi> not hearkning to his <hi>counſel,</hi> was <hi>ſlain</hi> in that <hi>Fight,</hi> together with the <hi>Flower</hi> of the <hi>Scots Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry:</hi> There are enough which will <hi>ſow Pillows</hi> under the <hi>elbows</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> and <hi>flatter</hi> them even in their <hi>evils;</hi> for (as one ſays) <hi>as ſoon a hot</hi> May <hi>without Flies, as Courts without Flatterers:</hi> But 'twere well if the <hi>Chambers</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> were ſometimes open to the perſons of <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>well-affected Plebeians,</hi> who being but <hi>ſtanders by</hi> (to ſpeak proverbially) yet many times may ſee more than the <hi>Gameſters;</hi> and their plain and ſober Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels may be improved for publick benefit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The other inſtance is mentioned in <hi>Roger Hoveden,</hi> and quoted by <hi>Speed,</hi> our own <hi>Chroniclers.</hi> King <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt gave admittance to a poor <hi>Hermit</hi> coming to him, to <hi>reprove</hi> him for his <hi>evils,</hi> to <hi>adviſe</hi> him of his <hi>danger,</hi> and to preach <hi>repentance</hi> to him; which <hi>advice,</hi> though at firſt he ſeemed to neglect, yet afterwards upon a fit of <hi>ſickneſs,</hi> he did ſeriouſly <hi>reflect</hi> upon, and in ſome degree <hi>governed</hi> himſelf accordingly; ſo that <hi>Hoveden</hi> breaks forth into this pathetical exclamation, <hi>How glorious is it for a Prince to begin and end his actions in him, who is beginning without beginning, and who judgeth the ends of the earth?</hi> Speed, p. 526. Book 9. Hoveden, fol. 428.</p>
               <p>But to return upon <hi>ſecond thoughts;</hi> notwithſtanding the above-mentioned <hi>encouraging Examples,</hi> I judged it fit to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe a <hi>Screen</hi> between the <hi>Rays</hi> of <hi>Majeſty</hi> and my <hi>mean ſelf:</hi> Some able Patron, my fellow Witneſſes, and my ſelf ſtand in need of, in regard of the many fears and diſcouragements we lye under from without; and therefore I pitched upon a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caenas</hi> near to our <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> that we may have a <hi>Friend</hi> next the <hi>Throne,</hi> who, in all <hi>juſt</hi> things might take our parts, if falſe whiſperings and dilations concerning us, ſhould at any time approach the <hi>Royal preſence.</hi> 'Tis true, for <hi>my ſelf,</hi> I have not hitherto appeared in any publick <hi>Tryal,</hi> as a Witneſs for His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> that part of my <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>ſervice</hi> (if <hi>God</hi> give life and health to perform it) is yet to come, when publick <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:97685:4"/>
of State</hi> (to which all <hi>private</hi> perſons muſt ſubmit) ſhall call for, and appoint ſuch <hi>Tryals:</hi> My <hi>Informations</hi> have been only preſented to ſome of His <hi>Majesties Justices</hi> upon <hi>Oath,</hi> as alſo to His <hi>Majesty</hi> himſelf in <hi>Council,</hi> which it ſeems, have appeared ſo <hi>conſiderable</hi> to the <hi>adverſe party,</hi> that one night, as I was <hi>walking</hi> to my <hi>Lodging,</hi> I was <hi>ſtab'd,</hi> and fell'd to the ground; upon which the <hi>intended Murtherer</hi> fled, ſuppoſing he had done his <hi>work;</hi> but it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to <hi>elude</hi> his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to preſerve <hi>me</hi> for his further <hi>ſervice,</hi> I hope for his <hi>glory,</hi> and for the good of his <hi>Church;</hi> the particular manner of that <hi>aſſault</hi> is accounted for in the following <hi>Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould not have inſtanced in the danger of ſo <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>worthleſs</hi> a <hi>thing</hi> as my ſelf, if the greateſt <hi>Patriots,</hi> and ſome of them, either now, or lately <hi>Aſſeſſors</hi> with your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> at the ſame <hi>Royal Board,</hi> were not threatned to be ſerved after the ſame manner; whom as <hi>God</hi> hath hitherto miraculouſly preſerved, ſo I hope he will <hi>entail</hi> the ſame <hi>protection</hi> on your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> who doth <hi>ſucceed</hi> and <hi>inherit</hi> their places both in <hi>Cares</hi> and <hi>Councels,</hi> which is the daily prayer of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My LORD,</salute>
                  <signed>Your Honours in all humble and dutiful obſervance, <hi>LAWRENCE MOWBRAY.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:97685:4"/>
               <head>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> Lord Mayor of the Famous City of <hi>London.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IN brisk and dangerous <hi>Onſets, double</hi> Armour is of great uſe, eſpecially to <hi>thoſe</hi> whoſe <hi>ſervice</hi> is in the <hi>Front,</hi> and who are likely to endure the brunt of the <hi>Enemy's</hi> aſſault. I am called forth with the reſt of my <hi>Fellow-Witneſſes,</hi> for His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> to ſtand the <hi>charge</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Battalions,</hi> who have ſet themſelves in <hi>Array</hi> againſt the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> our <hi>King, Kingdom,</hi> and eſpecially againſt the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> as the ſtrongeſt <hi>Bulwarks</hi> of all the <hi>Three.</hi> No marvel then, if when the <hi>City's</hi> danger is diſcovered, I chuſe alſo a <hi>City-Patron</hi> (as <hi>another mighty Second,</hi> I might ſay <hi>Firſt</hi>) to defend a <hi>juſt cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do aſſume this boldneſs to my ſelf, upon a double Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count:</p>
               <p n="1">I. That Supreme <hi>Dignity</hi> which your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> holds by juſt <hi>Merit,</hi> amongſt your <hi>worthy Citizens,</hi> as their <hi>chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> and <hi>Head</hi> of <hi>their Government,</hi> for this year, renders you <hi>able</hi> to protect me.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Your <hi>exemplary prudence</hi> and <hi>care,</hi> as well as <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>activity</hi> for the prevention of the <hi>Evils</hi> which are hereafter diſcovered, by the <hi>vogue</hi> of all good men do make you a <hi>willing Patron</hi> to all thoſe who are <hi>Co-operators</hi> in that work. And herein your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> ſolicitude for the <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> hath not (as far as I know) been tranſmitted to the <hi>imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of <hi>others</hi> in any <hi>Print,</hi> though indeed it deſerves to be writ with a <hi>Pen</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> and the <hi>point</hi> of a <hi>Diamond,</hi> in moſt <hi>durable Characters,</hi> for your <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Renown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I count it therefore a <hi>Felicity</hi> to me, to have the <hi>opportunity</hi> of being the <hi>firſt publick Admirer</hi> and <hi>Encomiaſt</hi> of your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> known actings againſt all <hi>Popiſh Conſpirators</hi> (I mean from the <hi>Preſs</hi>); which office, though your own <hi>worth</hi> doth loudly call for at my hands, yet (as I intimated before) I do undertake the <hi>Province</hi> much upon the ſcore of my own <hi>ſelf-defence,</hi> whoſe danger doth excite me not to be contented with a ſingle <hi>Addreſs</hi> for <hi>protection</hi> to the <hi>Lord High Chancellor</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but doth further prompt to accumulate <hi>ſecurity</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97685:5"/>
by the <hi>acceſſion</hi> of your <hi>Lordſhips favour,</hi> which I do hereby humbly ſupplicate and entreat. I muſt needs ſay, by what I have heard amongſt the <hi>Romanists</hi> in their <hi>Cabals,</hi> That your <hi>City</hi> is looked upon by <hi>them</hi> as the <hi>Grand Emporium</hi> of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> (as they call it) as well as the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> for you are criminated by <hi>them</hi> as the <hi>higheſt Countenancers</hi> and <hi>Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragers</hi> of the moſt <hi>Reformed Protestantiſm</hi> and its <hi>Profeſſors;</hi> ſo that, as not long ſince (as I have heard) this <hi>Motto</hi> was writ upon one of the <hi>Gates</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> by a waggiſh Pen, <hi>Hoc eſt Collegium Jeſuitanum; ſatyrically</hi> intimating, that in regard the <hi>Counſels</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> did ſo much prevail there for the preſent, therefore the <hi>whole City</hi> was to be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but as one of their <hi>Great Colledges;</hi> ſo it is a <hi>true</hi> and more laudable <hi>Character</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London, Hoc eſt Aſylum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatorum;</hi> and this not in <hi>Paſquil, Lampoone,</hi> or as a brand of <hi>Infamy,</hi> but as an indeleble <hi>mark</hi> of the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence</hi> of its renowned <hi>Inhabitants</hi> for ever. For, as it is the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to be comprehenſive of his <hi>whole Creation;</hi> ſo, <hi>thoſe</hi> who are moſt <hi>like</hi> him, are <hi>larger</hi> in their <hi>Protections</hi> and <hi>Reliefs</hi> (of <hi>ſuch</hi> as are <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>quiet</hi> in their <hi>principles:</hi>) than other men.</p>
               <p>I add this laſt <hi>clauſe,</hi> becauſe I know that the <hi>cenſure</hi> of the <hi>Papists</hi> upon your <hi>City,</hi> is grounded not only upon your <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection</hi> of <hi>Eſtabliſhed Proteſtancy,</hi> according to the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> but alſo it hath reſpect to your <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>harbouring</hi> many <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>peaceable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters,</hi> which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> look upon to be more <hi>numerous</hi> amongſt <hi>you,</hi> than (proportionably) in any <hi>other part</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>whom,</hi> in regard of their <hi>awakened principles,</hi> they look upon as greater <hi>Contrariants</hi> than the <hi>formal ordinary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</hi> This indeed is the <hi>party</hi> which they would willingly <hi>cajole,</hi> at leaſt to <hi>ſilence</hi> (if it were poſſible); and I have heard it reſolved in <hi>Popiſh Juncto's,</hi> as an <hi>Argument</hi> fit to induce them to a <hi>paſſive compliance,</hi> that the <hi>community</hi> of <hi>Sufferings</hi> ſhould be propounded to them. The <hi>Laws</hi> againſt <hi>Diſſenters</hi> and <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists</hi> being (in ſome things) as <hi>ſevere</hi> as againſt the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</hi> But hitherto they have not been able to obtain their <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired end,</hi> but have loſt all their <hi>ſolicitations</hi> in this matter: And I have heard ſome <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, <hi>They did diſpair of ever doing any good that way:</hi> For though <hi>civil reſpects</hi> may paſs as to the <hi>common</hi> offices of humane <hi>Life,</hi> between <hi>perſons</hi> of <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb facs="tcp:97685:5"/>
Religions;</hi> yet when <hi>principles,</hi> in which <hi>oppoſitions</hi> have their deepeſt <hi>root,</hi> do fight againſt <hi>principles;</hi> ſuch <hi>parties</hi> can never heartily <hi>unite.</hi> I mention this, that a <hi>juſt regard</hi> may be had in all our <hi>Governors,</hi> towards the <hi>peaceable</hi> and <hi>well-affected</hi> of that <hi>Claſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Lord,</hi> I have not, in what I have done, acted out of <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate malice</hi> or <hi>revenge</hi> againſt any mans <hi>perſon,</hi> but have only been ſtimulated by the <hi>pricks</hi> of my own <hi>conſcience,</hi> to prevent thoſe <hi>miſchiefs</hi> which, I knew, were <hi>impending</hi> upon our <hi>King,</hi> this <hi>City,</hi> and the <hi>whole Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And herein I confeſs a <hi>prize</hi> was put into my hands, to have been the <hi>first Diſcoverer</hi> of this <hi>Bloody Plot</hi> in the year 1676. But I muſt acknowledg, that through the power of <hi>contrary temptations,</hi> I did <hi>ſuccumb;</hi> and yet I was not altogether <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtifiable</hi> in my <hi>thoughts;</hi> in that I undertook a journey to <hi>London,</hi> from the <hi>North,</hi> on purpoſe to make this <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> ſo that my <hi>early deſires</hi> may ſomewhat <hi>atone</hi> for my <hi>ſlow</hi> and <hi>tardy actings;</hi> For which, as I have obtained His <hi>Majesties Gracious pardon,</hi> ſo I hope your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> will be moderate in your <hi>judgment</hi> concerning me, ſeeing the <hi>Impediments</hi> I was then to <hi>wrestle</hi> withal, ſeemed to me <hi>Invincible,</hi> as hereafter in the <hi>following Narrative</hi> is declared. And the truth is, I did <hi>quiet</hi> my <hi>conſcience</hi> at that <hi>time</hi> by ſuggeſting, that I reſerved my ſelf for the <hi>diſcloſing</hi> the <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> ſome <hi>other time,</hi> when the <hi>danger</hi> was <hi>nearer hand,</hi> and the <hi>deſign</hi> more <hi>ripe</hi> for execution; Herein, though I was prevented by <hi>others,</hi> yet the <hi>ſcheme</hi> of my thoughts being thus laid open, will, I hope, <hi>alleviate</hi> my <hi>cenſure</hi> amongſt <hi>good men.</hi> There are <hi>ſome particulars illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> of what is hereafter <hi>declared,</hi> which may be ſpoken to, when I am called upon to <hi>appear</hi> at any <hi>Tryal,</hi> as an <hi>Evidence</hi> for His <hi>Majesty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall ſay no more to your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> at this time, but craving <hi>pardon</hi> for my boldneſs, and recommending <hi>your Lordſhip</hi> with your <hi>great charge,</hi> the <hi>Honourable City of London,</hi> to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Protection,</hi> I humbly ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Lordſhips in all just and Christian ſervice, <hi>LAWRENCE MOWBRAY.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97685:6"/>
               <head>AN Introductory Preface.</head>
               <p>I Think it not amiſs, before I mention my <hi>Informations,</hi> to give the <hi>Reader</hi> ſome account of <hi>my ſelf,</hi> and the <hi>oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity</hi> I have had of being acquainted with this <hi>black de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> and the <hi>methods</hi> I took to <hi>diſcover</hi> the ſame after I was convinced of the <hi>evil</hi> thereof; which laſt clauſe I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe, being <hi>falſly principled</hi> by the <hi>Romiſh Prieſts</hi> at <hi>firſt,</hi> I thought it a <hi>meritorious work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The place of my <hi>Nativity</hi> was <hi>Worceſterſhire;</hi> but my <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> removing his whole <hi>Family</hi> into <hi>York-ſhire</hi> in my <hi>Infancy,</hi> I <hi>there</hi> received my <hi>Education</hi> in my <hi>youth,</hi> and that in the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> as eſtabliſhed in the <hi>Church of England;</hi> I was brought up in a <hi>Grammar-School,</hi> in order to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity;</hi> but other <hi>circumstances</hi> not concurring, and the times ſeeming not to look <hi>ſmilingly</hi> upon <hi>learned</hi> men, my <hi>friends</hi> were diverted from thoſe thoughts, and I was to wait for a more <hi>favourable</hi> opportunity.</p>
               <p>In this <hi>Interval,</hi> being about 18 years of Age, I was dealt with by ſome <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> to reſide a-while in Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoignes</hi> Houſe; not upon the <hi>ſtrict</hi> terms of a <hi>ſervant,</hi> but as an <hi>ingenuous attendant,</hi> or rather <hi>expectant</hi> of a better <hi>fortune,</hi> till the <hi>Clouds</hi> blowing over, I might (as my <hi>intentions</hi> were) tranſplant my ſelf into the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity;</hi> and I was inclined to Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoignes;</hi> rather than to any other <hi>Family,</hi> becauſe he was repreſented to me as a <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>temperate</hi> perſon, and a <hi>good Example</hi> for <hi>Youth</hi> to imitate.</p>
               <p>I had not been long there, but I was dealt with by Sir <hi>THOMAS</hi> himſelf, the <hi>Lady TEMPEST,</hi> but eſpecially by <hi>Father R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SHTON,</hi> Confeſſor to Sir <hi>THOMAS,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97685:6"/>
and his whole <hi>Family,</hi> to turn to their <hi>Religion;</hi> the <hi>Arguments</hi> they uſed, were theſe, the <hi>Truth</hi> of their <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>certainty</hi> of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> therein; whereas <hi>Proteſtantiſm</hi> (as they alledged) was but a <hi>Novelty</hi> riſen up of <hi>late</hi> years; and the <hi>Souls</hi> of its <hi>Profeſſors</hi> were in great danger of <hi>Eternal Damnation,</hi> except they did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Mother-Church;</hi> and withall they uſed many <hi>alluring provocations,</hi> and <hi>flattering promiſes</hi> of great and large <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments,</hi> if ever it pleaſed <hi>God,</hi> to favour their <hi>Endeavours,</hi> that the <hi>Roman Religion</hi> ſhould again be eſtabliſhed in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which they told me they were in <hi>great</hi> hopes of, and that many <hi>heads,</hi> and <hi>hands,</hi> were at work in order to the <hi>effecting</hi> thereof.</p>
               <p>I, being not able to ſee thorow, thoſe pecious <hi>pretences,</hi> was <hi>inſnared</hi> by them, and accordingly, yielding to their <hi>inſinuations,</hi> was admitted into their <hi>Church,</hi> being thereupon in great <hi>favour</hi> with them, and daily <hi>Aſsiſtant</hi> to <hi>Father Ruſhton</hi> at the <hi>Altar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here (to note this by the way) the <hi>Zeal</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> doth upbraid the <hi>coldneſs</hi> and <hi>indifferency</hi> of many <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who upon the entertainment of <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Attendants</hi> little heed their <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> in reference to <hi>Religion,</hi> but ſuffer them to go on, without any endeavour to rectifie their <hi>underſtandings</hi> in caſe any <hi>errour</hi> reſide in them; as if it were only <hi>lawful</hi> for them to uſe the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of their <hi>Bodies,</hi> as they do their <hi>Oxen</hi> and <hi>Horſes,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard to <hi>cultivate</hi> their minds: whereas you ſhall hardly have a <hi>Servant</hi> admitted into a <hi>Popiſh Family,</hi> but they will ſift his <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Principles;</hi> and if he be a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> they will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to <hi>reduce</hi> him; and they eſteem themſelves under a <hi>Religious Obligation</hi> ſo to do, whoſe <hi>Zeal</hi> therein, if it were according to <hi>knowledge,</hi> might be <hi>inſtructive</hi> unto others, who ſtand upon a <hi>truer</hi> Foundation, and embrace <hi>righter Principles.</hi> This by the by.</p>
               <p>Being thus turned <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> as I have ſaid, I had oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to be admitted to the <hi>Privacies</hi> of <hi>Sir Tho. Gaſcoigne, Father Ruſhton,</hi> and others, in whoſe frequent <hi>Conſultations</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſes,</hi> both amongſt <hi>themſelves,</hi> and alſo with <hi>me,</hi> I ſoon found out the <hi>Intrigues</hi> of their <hi>Deſigns,</hi> and my mind was ſo aſtoniſhed at the thoughts of the <hi>King's Murder,</hi> and the <hi>Great Alterations,</hi> which were deſigned by <hi>them,</hi> to be accompliſhed in this <hi>Land,</hi> that, I not only returned to the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> in my heart, which I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>revolted</hi> from, and ſince, by <hi>God</hi>'s goodneſs, have re-made publick <hi>profeſsion</hi> of, but I <hi>reſolved</hi> alſo to repair to <hi>London,</hi> about the latter end of the year 1676. to make a <hi>Diſcovery</hi> of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97685:7"/>
what I knew in thoſe matters. And I had then a fair <hi>opportunity</hi> to diſengage my ſelf from <hi>Sir Tho. Gaſcoigne's Family,</hi> in regard the <hi>Laws,</hi> being ſtrict againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and at that time preſſed to be put in <hi>execution, Sir Thomas</hi> was willing to <hi>abridge</hi> the number of his <hi>Houſhold,</hi> leſt <hi>forfeitures</hi> ſhould grow <hi>high</hi> upon <hi>them;</hi> taking therefore that <hi>occaſion,</hi> I withdrew from that <hi>Houſe,</hi> and a while after undertook a <hi>Journey</hi> to <hi>London</hi> about <hi>May</hi> 1677. long before Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> had made any publick Diſcovery of a <hi>Plot,</hi> and yet the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> had ſome <hi>jealouſie</hi> of my <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy</hi> in their <hi>Religion;</hi> and being alſo <hi>conſcious</hi> to themſelves, that I could diſcover a <hi>great part</hi> of their <hi>guilt,</hi> they uſed many <hi>menaces</hi> againſt me, even to my <hi>very face,</hi> which I <hi>eluded,</hi> as well as I could.</p>
               <p>Coming to <hi>London,</hi> under the <hi>diſcouragement</hi> of many circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as my being of <hi>ſmall</hi> acquaintance at <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore not <hi>capable</hi> of making any <hi>creditable</hi> applications to the <hi>Court;</hi> moreover highly <hi>threatned</hi> by the <hi>Papiſh</hi> Party, both in the <hi>Country,</hi> and in <hi>London,</hi> beſides juding it <hi>ridiculous</hi> in me, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>alone,</hi> to appear againſt ſo great a <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Opponents</hi> (for I then knew of no <hi>other</hi> evidence, but <hi>my ſelf</hi>) I was ſo far <hi>intimida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> and <hi>diſheartened</hi> in my <hi>undertaking,</hi> as to return to <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> again <hi>reintecta,</hi> and without making any <hi>Diſcovery</hi> at all; but ſtill under great <hi>inquietude,</hi> and <hi>diſſatisfaction,</hi> becauſe I could not eaſe my <hi>mind,</hi> in making the <hi>Diſcovery</hi> I intended.</p>
               <p>Arriving again in the <hi>Country,</hi> the <hi>pricks</hi> of my <hi>conſcience</hi> did <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> me thither, inſomuch that I could have no <hi>reſt,</hi> till I had wrote up a <hi>Letter</hi> to a Great <hi>Perſon</hi> at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> acquainting him, (as from an <hi>unknown</hi> hand) with the <hi>deſigned Murther</hi> of His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and the Great <hi>Danger</hi> the <hi>Kingdom</hi> was in, by thoſe <hi>underhand ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations;</hi> the <hi>Copy</hi> of which <hi>Letter,</hi> in regard it was the <hi>Embrio</hi> of my <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> I have here annexed.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>How long I have concealed the intended and immediate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of ſome diſloyal and traiterous perſons (from whoſe merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and bloody Deſign God bleſs our <hi>Soveraign Lord the King.</hi> It is now full time, I think, to declare, (though not in hopes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) but as a true and loyal Subject to my King) the wicked and deſperate Deſign of ſome <hi>Papiſt</hi> Conſpirators, &amp;c. That by an immediate <hi>inſurrection</hi> to proceed with Fire and Sword until they have altered the Government, or ſettled the <hi>Crown</hi> (God
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97685:7"/>
bleſs <hi>King Charles the Second</hi>) upon the <hi>head</hi> of ſome other, ſo by conſequence the death of the <hi>King</hi> is conſpired, and ſought for: This <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> my Lord, is of no little ſtanding, but, to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, contrived almoſt this <hi>three years</hi> ago, and now come to the height of a deſperate <hi>reſolution:</hi> My heart is loyal and true to the <hi>King,</hi> but I muſt confeſs that through the perſwaſion and urging of Father <hi>Riſhton,</hi> &amp;c. I have my ſelf ſubſcribed to this <hi>wicked Deſign,</hi> and now am forced, as well through <hi>Loyalty</hi> to my <hi>King,</hi> as to clear my <hi>ſtained conſcience</hi> from that foul Deſign, it to reveal; and will endeavour hereafter to diſcover and procure a <hi>Liſt</hi> of theſe <hi>Conſpirators,</hi> which I have ſeen and ſubſcribed to. But I am certain of the after-mentioned perſons (with many others) are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the <hi>Liſt,</hi> and great <hi>Promoters</hi> of this <hi>Act;</hi> and are ſtill providing both <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Arms</hi> for their carrying on their Deſign. <hi>My Lord,</hi> I moſt humbly beg your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> pardon for this my boldneſs, intreating your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> as a true <hi>Royaliſt,</hi> to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate theſe <hi>Lines</hi> to whom your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> thinks moſt convenient. At preſent, <hi>my Lord,</hi> I dare not ſubſcribe my name, for ſeveral rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but at any time upon protection from theſe <hi>Papiſts,</hi> (being at preſent within their claws) I ſhall acknowledge the hand and mark ſubſcribed, as to proceed from</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt faithful and obedient Servant, and to the King</hi> a Loyal and faithful Subject.</signed>
                        <dateline>York <date>Jan. 1. 77/8.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Theſe perſons names who have ſubſcribed that at preſent I remember, were —<hi>Inglesby,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Gaſcoigne, Tho. Gaſcoigne</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Sir <hi>Miles Stapleton</hi> Barronet, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But the ſaid Letter being ſent by me, by the <hi>Common Poſt,</hi> and from one unknown, I did therefore doubt whether it might come to the hands of that <hi>Noble-man</hi> to whom it was directed, or if it did, how it would be reſented in regard of the <hi>extraordinary No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty</hi> of the thing; wherefore I did not think my ſelf to have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently diſcharged my <hi>conſcience,</hi> in ſuch a <hi>Criſis</hi> of danger meerly upon the ſending of that Letter, without ſeconding the <hi>Contents</hi> thereof by farther Applications; therefore afterwards being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the appearance of others in this caſe, I did reſort to ſome <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire, viz. Juſtice Tyndall,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice Lowther,</hi> before whom I being examined upon <hi>Oath,</hi> made a ſhort <hi>Scheme</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Deſign,</hi> as by the Copy of the Examination before them, hereunto annexed may appear.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97685:8"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Information of <hi>Lawrence Mowbray</hi> of <hi>Leeds,</hi> taken before us upon Oath this ſixteenth day of <hi>Auguſt. 1679.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THE Informant ſaith, that in the year 1675. to the beſt of his knowledg, he being at Sir <hi>Tho. Gaſcoignes,</hi> he the ſaid Sir <hi>Tho.</hi> ordered the Informant to draw a Conveyance of his whole Eſtate to Sir <hi>Will. Inglesby,</hi> which Conveyance the Informant ſaith, he drew by the form of a Conveyance of Truſt made from Sir <hi>Miles Stapleton,</hi> of his whole Eſtate to Sir <hi>John Dawney.</hi> The Informant further ſaith, that though he was not witneſs to the aforeſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance of Sir <hi>Tho. Gaſcoigne,</hi> yet he heard from Sir <hi>Tho. Gaſcoigne</hi> that there was a Defeaſance to the ſaid Deed of Truſt, and from <hi>Rob. Bolron,</hi> and <hi>Matthias Hickeringill,</hi> that they were witneſſes to the ſaid Deed of Truſt. And further, he ſpeaketh not to the Deed of Truſt. The Informant further depoſeth, that in the year 1676. to the beſt of his remembrance, about <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigne, Tho. Gaſcoigne</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> the Lady <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> and <hi>William Riſhton</hi> Prieſt, &amp;c. being together in <hi>Barmebow</hi> Dining-room, he the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant heard them hold ſeveral diſcourſes concerning a Deſign of killing the King, firing the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>York;</hi> the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Tempeſt</hi> ſeemed to ſay jeaſtingly, if the Deſign did not take, they would all be poor Gentlemen; <hi>Tho. Gaſcoigne</hi> her Brother anſwered her, if it did not take effect, ſhe would partake of their ſufferings, being alſo concerned in it; they all concluded it would be a meritorious undertaking, and for the glory of the Church, and they would venture their Eſtates in it: The Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant further ſaith, there was then in the Houſe one Doctor <hi>Stapleton</hi> a Prieſt, who coming from another room, and finding the Informant at the door, went in, and deſired them in a low voice to forbear their Diſcourſe, for there was one at the door; Whereupon the Lady <hi>Tempeſt</hi> called in the Informant, and ſent him down to entertain ſome ſtrangers below. The Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant further depoſeth, that he had heard ſeveral Diſcourſes from Sir <hi>Tho. Gaſcoigne,</hi> and <hi>William Riſhton</hi> of a Religious Houſe or Nunnery was to be eſtabliſhed at <hi>Dolebank,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> would ſettle ninety pound <hi>per annum</hi> for their maintenance</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Taken before us
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Brad. Tindall.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Will. Lowther junior.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97685:8"/>This <hi>Examination</hi> being tranſmitted by the ſaid <hi>Juſtices</hi> to the <hi>Council,</hi> I ſoon after, <hi>viz. Auguſt</hi> 31. 1679. wrote a Letter to Sir <hi>John Nicholas,</hi> one of the Secretaries to His Majeſty's moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Privy-Council, (then in waiting) acquainting him, amongſt other things, that there were divers circumſtances, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to this diſcovery, very material, which were not inſerted in my Information made before the ſaid Juſtices, but ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by me, when ever the Honourable Council would be pleaſed to command a full account from me.</p>
               <p>In Anſwer to which Letter, I received the following, dated and ſubſcribed as followeth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Council-Chamber in</hi> Whitehall, <date>Sept. 5. 1679.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>VVHereas by your Letter of the <hi>31th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, directed to Sir <hi>John Nicholas,</hi> which hath this day been read to the Lords of His Majeſty's moſt Honourable Privy-Council, you make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that there are divers circumſtances very material, relating to the Information you have given, that are not therein inſerted; and that you are willing, when ever the Council pleaſes, to give a full account thereof. I am, by their Lordſhips command, to pray and require you to make your repair hither by the <hi>29th</hi> day of this inſtant <hi>September,</hi> that you may be ready to give their Lordſhips ſuch farther Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as you have to acquaint them with, on the Firſt of <hi>October</hi> next. Their Lordſhips have promiſed, that care ſhall be taken for the defray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the charges of your Journey, which being all I have in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to ſignifie to you, I remain,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        <signed>Your very humble Servant, <hi>THOMAS DOLMAN.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This noble Invitation and Summons was ſent unto me by a Meſſenger on purpoſe, ſuperſcribed, <hi>To Mr. Lawrence Mowbray, at his Houſe in York-ſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>According to the tenor thereof, I did, as in Duty bound, repair to <hi>London,</hi> and by Order, gave in a larger Information upon Oath before <hi>Edmund Warcup,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> one of His Majeſty's Juſtices of the Peace, for the County of <hi>Middleſex</hi> and City of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> a Copy whereof is hereunto annexed.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97685:9"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>[Middleſex and Weſtminſter]</hi> The Information of <hi>Lawrence Mowbray,</hi> of <hi>Leeds,</hi> in the County of <hi>York,</hi> Gent. taken upon Oath the Second day of <hi>October, 1679.</hi> before me <hi>Edmund Warcup,</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> one of His Majeſty's Juſtices of the Peace in the ſaid County and City.</head>
                     <p>THis Informant ſaith, That when he was examined before Mr. <hi>Tindall</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lowther,</hi> two of His Majeſty's Juſtices of the Peace in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> in <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt paſt, he did not diſcover the whole of what he knew, in Relation to the late horrid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, in regard he had ſome doubts of his ſafety in that County amongſt thoſe Papiſts, whom he was to detect, and who threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſuch as they feared would diſcover the ſaid Deſigns; and for that this Informant conceived the danger he had run by conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But now this Informant will tell his knowledge of the Plot, beſeeching His Majeſty's gracious Pardon. This Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant being now ſent for up, by Order of His Majeſty's moſt honourable Privy-Council, conceiveth himſelf under their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, hopes they will intercede for his Pardon to His Majeſty; and on that confidence ſaith, That in the year 1674. he came to Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign</hi>'s, and was with him in his Chamber till <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> 1676. and in that time he obſerved Mr. <hi>Thomas Addiſon,</hi> then Prieſt to Mrs. <hi>Killingbeck,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fincham,</hi> Prieſt to Sir <hi>John Savill,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Twhing,</hi> Senior, Mr. <hi>Thomas Twhing,</hi> Junior, two <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts, Mr. <hi>Lodge,</hi> Dr. <hi>Stapleton</hi> (Brother to Sir <hi>Miles Stapleton</hi>) one <hi>Robert Killingbeck,</hi> and divers other <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts, ſeveral times to invite, and privately to confer with Mr. <hi>William Riſhton,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign</hi>'s Prieſt; and this Informant being deſired to aſſiſt, and be as obliging as he could to the ſaid <hi>Riſhton,</hi> and to attend him at the Altar at Maſs, became in great favour with him, and was permitted to continue in the ſaid Mr. <hi>Riſhton</hi>'s Chamber when the Prieſts were in private with him: And he very often heard them diſcourſe of a Deſign, laid for the ſetting the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Religion uppermoſt in <hi>England,</hi> and how likely the ſame was to ſucceed, in regard moſt of the conſiderable Papiſts had undertaken to act for it: And that if the ſaid Deſign was not to be compaſſed by fair and lawful means, then it was to be done
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97685:9"/>
by Fire and Sword; and particularly they declared, That <hi>London</hi> and <hi>York</hi> were to be fired, and then the ſame courſe was to be taken in other places: And that being begun, the ſame Deſign was to be proſecuted with the Sword alſo, and that force was to be made uſe of, for deſtroying the <hi>Heretics</hi> and Oppoſers of this Deſign. And they ſeveral times farther ſaid, That the King, when he was in his Exile, had promiſed to Eſtabliſh their Religion, if ever he were reſtored; but that hitherto he had not performed that promiſe, and therefore he was adjudged a <hi>Heretic,</hi> and was to be killed, if he did not ſuddenly Eſtabliſh the <hi>Catholic</hi> Religion, which they now diſpaired that he would do.</p>
                     <p>And this Informant further ſaith, That Mr. <hi>William Riſhton</hi> did one day acquaint Mr. <hi>Addiſon,</hi> that he had according to agreement given the Sacrament of ſecrecy to Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign,</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> to Mr. <hi>Stephen Tempeſt,</hi> and to the Lady <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> and others, in Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign</hi>'s Chappel, and had thereupon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to them the whole Deſign; and that they had ſeverally engaged to be ſecret, faithful, and active, to their utmoſt powers, in carrying on the ſaid Deſign; and would thereto contribute as far as their Eſtates would permit. And required an account of the ſaid <hi>Addiſon,</hi> and of as many other Prieſts (beſides thoſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named) as came to him, how far they had proceeded therein, who anſwered the ſaid <hi>Riſhton,</hi> That they, in the ſeveral Families and places they were intereſted in, had given the like Sacrament of ſecrecy to their ſeveral Friends; and had thereupon acquainted them with the Deſign, and the ways and means intended to carry it on; and that their Friends approved thereof, and promiſed to contribute their utmoſt Intereſt, Power, and Eſtates, for advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Catholic</hi> Religion.</p>
                     <p>And this Informant farther ſaith, That by perſuaſion of the ſaid <hi>William Riſhton,</hi> who was his Confeſſor, he likewiſe received from his hand the Sacrament of ſecrecy. And this Informant very well remembreth, that about <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> 1676. there was an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of many of the Prieſts afore-named, and others, whoſe Names this Informant cannot remember, at Mr. <hi>Riſhton</hi>'s Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where they did all agree, and declare, that the King ſhould be killed, for that the Pope had Excommunicated him; and it was not lawful only, but meritorious to deſtroy and kill any <hi>Heretic</hi> whatſoever, and that when the King was killed, Fire and Sword was to be imployed againſt all ſuch as ſhould oppoſe the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97685:10"/>
of the <hi>Catholic</hi> Religion in <hi>England,</hi> and that all or moſt of the <hi>Catholics</hi> had ingaged themſelves in the ſaid undertaking.</p>
                     <p>After which diſcourſe, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Riſhton</hi> told the ſaid Prieſts, he had a Liſt of many Papiſts who were engaged in the Deſign, and did produce a Liſt of Names, containing about 4 or 5 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, to the beſt of this Informant's Obſervation, all whom, he ſaid, were engaged in the Deſign; many of which Names he read unto them, and amongſt them, this Informant very well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth he read the Names of Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign, Thomas Gaſcoign,</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Mr. <hi>Middleton,</hi> Sir <hi>Miles Stapleton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sherburn, Richard Townley,</hi> and <hi>Francis Townley,</hi> the Lady <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stephen Tempeſt,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Hungate,</hi> Sir <hi>John Savill,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Vavoſor,</hi> and his eldeſt Son Dr. <hi>Peter Vavoſor, Edward</hi> and <hi>Thomas Killingbeck, Barney, Robert Doleman, Marwood, Thomas Priſcick,</hi> and many others, (whoſe Names this Informant now remembreth not) were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſaid Liſt.</p>
                     <p>And the Informant farther ſaith, That Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign</hi> did often bid this Informant to write Superſcriptions to ſeveral Letters, ſome whereof were directed to Mr. <hi>William Harcourt,</hi> others to Mr. <hi>Corker,</hi> others to Mr. <hi>Cornwallis</hi> in <hi>London;</hi> and ſome of the ſaid Letters to Mr. <hi>Cornwallis,</hi> were directed to him by the Name of <hi>Pracid;</hi> other Letters by like order this Informant directed to Mrs. <hi>Laſſells,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Twhing,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Beckwith,</hi> who were to be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſſes, or to have other Offices in the Nunnery erected at <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank,</hi> to which the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign</hi> contributed 90 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> and made a ſettlement of an Eſtate at <hi>Mauſton,</hi> the Tenant's name whereof was <hi>Alvery Lofthouſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And this Informant farther ſaith, That he often heard the ſaid Prieſts in Mr. <hi>Riſhton</hi>'s Chamber ſay, That they had Commiſſion from the Pope to proſecute the ſaid Deſign by all likely ways, and that all the Jeſuits were particularly engaged in the ſaid Deſign, and were to be the managers thereof: And that the Prieſts through <hi>England</hi> were to aſſiſt therein, and engage all the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies therein, where they had any Intereſt. And they did alſo tell one another, that ſums of Money was collected for buying of Arms for carrying on the Deſign; and that ſeveral of their Friends had paid in't their ſhares for that purpoſe. And they ſometimes ſaid, That they had Orders from the Pope to be as brief in their proſecution as poſſibly they could, that they might proceed to Execution: And that they did communicate their ſeveral Letters
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97685:10"/>
from their Friends beyond Sea, to the perſons whom they had perſuaded into this Work. And they alſo affirmed, That the Pope would in a little time determin a ſettlement of both Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical and Civil Preferments, upon the Actors and Contributors of this meritorious Deſign (as they termed it). And that the Pope had Excommunicated the King, and all other <hi>Heretics,</hi> in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and had granted a Plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of ten thouſand years to thoſe who ſhould act, either Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally, or in Eſtate, to kill the King, or any other <hi>Heretic,</hi> for promotion of their Religion, beſides a Pardon, and other grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications.</p>
                     <p>And this Informant farther ſaith, That by the command of Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign,</hi> he went to <hi>Robert Bolron,</hi> to direct him to go to Father <hi>Ruſhton,</hi> to reconcile him to the <hi>Catholic</hi> Church, which was performed accordingly.</p>
                     <p>And he farther ſaith, That the Paper now produced, dated the Firſt of <hi>January,</hi> 1677/8. hereunto annexed, is all of this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant's hand writing, and is a Copy of a Letter which he directed to a Perſon of Quality at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and that he ſent the ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the Poſt from <hi>Leeds</hi> to <hi>London</hi> on the Firſt of <hi>January,</hi> on which day this Informant wrote the ſaid Copy hereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Jurat</hi> 
                           <date>die &amp; anno ſuperdict.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Coram me <hi>Edmund Warcup.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Afterwards His Majeſty having received Informations of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſons in the Counties of <hi>York, Northumberland, Lancaſhire,</hi> and Biſhoppric of <hi>Durham,</hi> who were ſuſpected to be Papiſts, or favourers of Popery, or who could give Information touching the Plot againſt His Majeſty, was pleaſed to employ my ſelf, and <hi>Robert Bolron,</hi> Gentleman, to repair into thoſe parts, and to execute that Commiſſion which is contained in the following Order of Council.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order_of_Council">
                  <body>
                     <p>VVHereas Information hath been given to His Majeſty in Council upon Oath, That the ſeveral perſons in the Liſt annexed mentioned, are ſuſpected to be favourers of Papiſts, and to harbour and lodge Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits, and to have in their keeping Writings and Papers, relating either to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97685:11"/>
horrid Plot againſt the Life of His Sacred Majeſty, and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or to Colluſive conveyances of Lands to ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious uſes; His Majeſty was thereupon pleaſed to command, and accordingly We do hereby Will and Require all and every of His Majeſty's Juſtices of the Peace, to whom the Bearers hereof; <hi>Laurence Mowbray</hi> and <hi>Robert Bolron,</hi> or either of them, ſhall make Application, to receive in due form of Law, the Informations they ſhall exhibit againſt all, or any of the ſaid perſons in the Liſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, or any others, which the ſaid <hi>Laurence Mowbray</hi> and <hi>Robert Bolron</hi> ſhall juſtly ſuſpect to be concerned in the aforeſaid Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and thereupon to proceed according to Law, for the more ſpeedy and effectual diſcovery of the Offenders, and bringing them to condign Puniſhment. And the ſaid Juſtices of Peace are hereby further required, to iſſue out their Warrants (if they ſee occaſion) for ſearching the reſpective Houſes of the ſeveral perſons in the ſaid Liſt mentioned, or any other ſuſpected Houſes, as well for Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits, as for Papers, Letters, Crucifixes, <hi>Agnus Dei's,</hi> Popiſh Books and Veſtments, and other ſuperſtitious Trinkers; and to proceed according to Law againſt ſuch Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits, as ſhall be apprehended: And alſo to diſpoſe of ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Letters, Crucifixes, <hi>Agnus Dei's,</hi> Popiſh Books and Veſtments, and other ſuperſtitious Trinkets as ſhall be found in the ſaid ſearch, as the Law directs; except ſuch Papers or Writings as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the ſaid Plot, which are to be ſafely conveyed unto us with all ſpeed: And of what the ſaid Juſtices of the Peace, or any of them, ſhall do in purſuance of this His Majeſty's Pleaſure, they are to return unto us from time to time an exact account. For all which, this ſhall be unto them, and every of them, a ſufficient Warrant.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Dated at the <hi>Council-Chamber</hi> in <hi>Whitehall</hi> 
                           <date>the 17th day of <hi>October,</hi> 1679.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Angleſey,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Lauderdale,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Henry Coventry,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Bridgewater,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Fra. North.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Sunderland,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>J. Ernle,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>John Nicholas.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>According to which Order, Mr. <hi>Bolron,</hi> and my ſelf, with the aſſiſtance of ſome of His Majeſty's Meſſengers, repaired into the Northern Parts, where in obedience to the ſaid Commiſſion, and in purſuance thereof, I made the two following Informations.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97685:11"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>[Civitas Ebor.]</dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <head>The Information of <hi>Lawrence Mowbray,</hi> taken upon Oath the 27th day of <hi>October, 1679.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>who ſaith and depoſeth,</opener>
                     <p>THat about <hi>Michaelmas, Anno</hi> 1676. there was an Aſſembly of ſeveral Prieſts or Jeſuits at the Houſe of Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign,</hi> at <hi>Barmbow,</hi> in the County of <hi>York;</hi> and that the ſaid Aſſembly did then generally conclude and agree, That the King (meaning the King of <hi>England</hi>) was to be kill'd, for that he was a <hi>Heretic,</hi> and Excommunicated by the Pope, and that it was not only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but meritorious to kill the ſaid King, or any other <hi>Heretic;</hi> and that they likewiſe ſaid, That all, or moſt of the <hi>Catholics</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> were engaged in the ſame Deſign. After which diſcourſe, one <hi>William Ruſhton,</hi> Prieſt to Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign,</hi> produced a Liſt of Names, which he did declare were engaged in, and contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries to the ſaid Deſign. And farther depoſeth, That the ſaid <hi>William Ruſhton</hi> read over many of the Names of the ſaid Liſt in the hearing of this Informant, amongſt which he mentioned <hi>Robert Dolman,</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> And this Informant farther depoſeth, That Dr. <hi>Peter Vavoſor</hi>'s Name was in the Liſt aforeſaid.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Capt. &amp; jurat</dateline>
                        <signed>coram <hi>Richard Shaw,</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <signed>Major &amp; als. Lawrence Mowbray.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>[<hi>County of</hi> York <hi>and</hi> Lancaſter.] </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <head>The Information of <hi>Lawrence Mowbray,</hi> taken upon Oath the Second of <hi>November, 1679.</hi> before us <hi>Henry Marſden,</hi> and <hi>John Aſhton,</hi> Eſquires; two of His Majeſty's Juſtices of the Peace for the ſaid Counties.</head>
                     <p>AT an Aſſembly of divers Popiſh Prieſts at Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoign</hi>'s, at <hi>Barm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow,</hi> was produced a Liſt of Names, who were concerned and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butors to a Deſign of killing the King, and Eſtabliſhing the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and amongſt many others, there was the Names of Mr. <hi>Sherburn</hi> of <hi>Stonyhurſt, Walmesley</hi> of <hi>Dungney; Richard Townley</hi> and <hi>Francis Townley,</hi> of <hi>Townley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stephen Tempeſt</hi> of <hi>Braughton, Richard York,</hi> and divers others, which this Informant doth not at preſent remember.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Lawrence Mowbray.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:97685:12"/>The reſt of our time was ſpent in executing other parts of the ſaid Commiſſion, His Majeſty's Officers of Juſtice aſſiſting us in all places whither we came, and accordingly ſeveral Popiſh Trin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, Books, and Veſtments, were taken by us, and diſpoſed as the Law directs: And the effect of our Journey having been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to His Majeſty at our return, was graciouſly accepted, and entertained, both by himſelf, and by the whole Council; upon confidence of whole favour, I count it my Honour, as well as Duty, to ſtand ready to obſerve His Majeſty's farther Directions in any thing, which may hereafter conduce to the preſervation of His Perſon, and the Eſtabliſhment of the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> amongſt us.</p>
               <p>Mention having been made by me, of an Aſſault made upon me, the manner of it, as it was by His Majeſty's Command given in to him by Council, is as followeth:</p>
               <p>Upon <hi>October</hi> 14. 1679. I being to attend upon the Right Honourable the Lords, Commiſſioners of His Majeſty's <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury,</hi> at the <hi>Treaſury-Chamber</hi> at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> departed from thence about Six or Seven a Clock at night, and going over <hi>Leiceſter-Fields</hi> towards my Lodgings, at the <hi>Kings-Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Martin</hi>'s Lane, but intending in the way to call upon Mr. <hi>Bolron,</hi> at the <hi>Bear and Ragged-Staff</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter-Fields,</hi> I was overtaken about the middle of the Fields by a perſon unknown, whom I heard follow me very faſt; I ſuppoſed his ſpeed was to get out of the Rain; but as he came up to me, being on my left hand, he with a Dagger, or ſuch like Inſtrument, ſtabbed me upon my left breaſt, the thruſt entering my Coat and Waſtcoat, and lighting upon the Whale-bone of my Bodice, which, unknown to the bloody Aſſailant, I did wear for my convenience, it prevented his deſign; notwithſtanding by continuing his thruſt, I fell down to the ground, being ſlippery by reaſon of the Rain; the party then ran away, ſuppoſing that I had been ſlain: But ſtill I not daring to ſpeak or call out, leſt he ſhould renew his attempt while he was near; but preſently after his departure, I called a Link-boy, who was at the other ſide of the Fields, who lighted me to my Lodgings another way.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Lawrence Mowbray.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97685:12"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are juſtly look'd upon as having a <hi>Grand influence</hi> on the forementioned <hi>deſigns,</hi> I ſhall cloſe this <hi>dicourſe</hi> with a <hi>Scholaſtical velitation,</hi> which, I hope, will not be unacceptable to the <hi>learned;</hi> for it is worthy of a <hi>Pen</hi> far ſuperiour to <hi>mine:</hi> The <hi>queſtion</hi> I would <hi>diſcuſſe,</hi> is this,</p>
               <p>Whether that <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> in this <hi>our Age,</hi> may be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be at their <hi>vertical,</hi> or <hi>higheſt Exaltation?</hi> Whether they ſtand at a <hi>ſtay,</hi> or verge towards their <hi>declenſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Take the more boldneſs to propound ſuch a queſtion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a <hi>ſecular Prieſt</hi> hath led me the way: for <hi>Watſon</hi> in his firſt <hi>quodlibet,</hi> hath theſe two <hi>queries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> having gone aſtray from their <hi>firſt</hi> inſtitution, there be any likelihood of their <hi>continuance?</hi> or if not, of their <hi>downfall;</hi> and he inclines, perhaps <hi>prophetically,</hi> to this <hi>latter.</hi> Artic. 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether any danger to <hi>God's Church</hi> to <hi>erre,</hi> and utterly to be <hi>Overthrown</hi> by the <hi>Jeſuits ruin,</hi> (if it happen) or no <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at all?</hi> which he reſolves in the <hi>Negative.</hi> Artic. 10.</p>
               <p>I Know the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are much for <hi>Probable opinions;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in conſideration of their <hi>Riſe, Progreſs,</hi> and the <hi>Ways,</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> they have taken to <hi>advance</hi> themſelves, together with their <hi>immoral</hi> and <hi>unlawful</hi> practices; I ſhall propound the <hi>reaſons,</hi> why <hi>ſome</hi> men ſuppoſe, that <hi>they</hi> are at their <hi>height,</hi> or rather <hi>declining.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. Their <hi>Original</hi> is affirmed by ſome of their own <hi>Church</hi> to be by <hi>ſurprize, and impoſition</hi> upon the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> For upon the firſt coming of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and his <hi>Partners</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> the <hi>Rules</hi> of their <hi>order</hi> being preſented to <hi>him,</hi> he committed them to <hi>three Cardinals</hi> to examine, who thought good to <hi>refuſe</hi> them, becauſe their <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> to their <hi>General,</hi> was ſeemingly <hi>Superiour</hi> to their <hi>Subjection</hi> to the <hi>Pope;</hi> for <hi>Maffaus,</hi> ſpeaking of their <hi>General,</hi> ſays, <hi>without controverſie one muſt be choſen, to whom all muſt be obedient, as if it were to Chriſt, to his word they muſt ſwear, and eſteem his beck, and his will, as an Oracle of God, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>vit. Ignat. Cap.</hi> 9. I pray what greater obedience could the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf claim? hereupon being <hi>repuls'd,</hi> they <hi>reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> their <hi>Rule,</hi> and made their <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and their <hi>General</hi> both alike; for theſe be the words of <hi>Ribadeneira,</hi> who alſo afterward wrote the life <hi>of Ignatius. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>The order of theſe Clarks muſt be, that by their inſtitution, they be ready to obey the Pope at a beck, and live by ſuch a line, as he ſhall well conſider, and determine off.</hi> Upon the <hi>inſertion</hi> of which <hi>paſſage,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> having (as he thought) <hi>ſecured</hi> his own <hi>Authority,</hi> lent a more <hi>favourable ear</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97685:13"/>
                  <hi>confirmed</hi> their <hi>Order;</hi> yet with ſome <hi>jealouſie,</hi> and with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>ſcruples of Conſcience,</hi> as ſome of their own <hi>Authors</hi> ſpeak; for at firſt, he allowed them not to exceed the number of Sixty, and therefore well may their <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> begin with <hi>this little Congregation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To improve this <hi>Argument,</hi> if there be a <hi>worm</hi> in the <hi>Root,</hi> the <hi>verdure</hi> of any <hi>plant</hi> will in time <hi>decay. An Errour</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the <hi>firſt concoction,</hi> is never remedied in the <hi>ſecond,</hi> as <hi>Phyſicians</hi> ſay, no marvel then, if <hi>homebred-jealouſies</hi> do increaſe upon this <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> now grown <hi>numorous,</hi> if not <hi>formid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> to the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf; <hi>ab origine fuit Sic;</hi> and therefore not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their pretended <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> and <hi>vow</hi> to the <hi>Papal Chair;</hi> when the <hi>Pope</hi> Croſſes their purpoſes, as <hi>Xiſtus quintus</hi> did, he incurred their great <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> and <hi>hatred,</hi> to the <hi>ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> (as ſome think) of his <hi>life.</hi> After whoſe death, they moſt <hi>Maliciouſly</hi> depraved him, and <hi>preached</hi> againſt him <hi>openly</hi> in <hi>Spain:</hi> yea <hi>one</hi> of their <hi>Faction</hi> proceeded <hi>publiquely</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that <hi>Homo non Chriſtianus poſſit eſſe Romanus Pontifex,</hi> which <hi>Tenet</hi> amongſt them argued <hi>bitter ſpight,</hi> and <hi>unchriſtian diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain</hi> againſt their acknowledged <hi>Head, Watſon quodl. pag.</hi> 100.</p>
               <p>It is the worſt thing in the world to <hi>ſerve a jealous Maſter;</hi> for at one time, or other, his <hi>diſſatisfaction</hi> (though <hi>cover'd</hi> for a ſeaſon) will <hi>appear</hi> to the <hi>diſgrace,</hi> if not <hi>ruine,</hi> of his <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant:</hi> Let the <hi>Provincial</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Jeſuits,</hi> in the room of Mr. <hi>Whitebread,</hi> apply this to <hi>himſelf,</hi> and his <hi>Order,</hi> they are not quite <hi>ſecure</hi> on the <hi>otherſide</hi> the water. Beſides, <hi>Beneficia cóuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> grata, dum exſolvi poſſunt,</hi> as the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ſpeaketh. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <hi>Merit,</hi> which the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> pretent to, from his <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as <hi>voting</hi> themſelves to be the <hi>Chief,</hi> if not <hi>only</hi> ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <hi>Papal Chair,</hi> is but an <hi>upbraiding</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> who <hi>ſits</hi> therein; eſpecially in <hi>doubtful</hi> and <hi>ſuſpicious</hi> times, <hi>great deſerts</hi> in ſome Circumſtances render a man as <hi>obnoxious,</hi> as the <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est guilt;</hi> ſome give an inſtance in <hi>Marſhal Byron</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> in the days of their <hi>Henry the fourth;</hi> in the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> in <hi>Richard the third's</hi> time, and in the <hi>Old Earl</hi> of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> in <hi>Queen Elizabeth's</hi> days here in <hi>England.</hi> All which (ſay they) were <hi>depreſt,</hi> and broken under the weight of their <hi>merits</hi> to their reſpective <hi>Princes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>benefits</hi> procure ſuch <hi>requitals,</hi> what ſhall <hi>injuries do?</hi> For the Author of the <hi>Jeſuits Catechiſme,</hi> Chap. 25. Book. 3. ſays, <hi>That the notorious interprize, or uſurpation of the General of the Jeſuits over the Holy See, is ſuch, that there is no new Sect, which in time may be more prejudicial to it than this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. It is <hi>ominous</hi> and <hi>fatal</hi> to break a <hi>ſetled Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,</hi> on which an <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> is grounded; for the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Sanction</hi> is as the <hi>ſacred Bond</hi> or <hi>tye,</hi> which keeps that <hi>Order</hi> together. I will not trace the <hi>Converſation</hi> of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97685:13"/>
throughout all his Vows; but certainly in that of Poverty, and of not intermedling in ſecular Affairs, they have much deviated from their Primitive Inſtitution, and conſequently have made forfeiture of their Intereſt in the Priviledges of that <hi>Soda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is obſerved, That the eldeſt Children of Parents are more ſtrictly educated, than thoſe, which are born in their riper years; becauſe then the ſeverity of their Diſcipline melts into Lenity; and their Love, not guided by Reaſon, turns to fondneſs. The like probably may be affirmed of the firſt Inſtitutors of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who perhaps were ſtrict to their Rules; but the declining therefrom of their poſterity, argues an old and doting Age, in the Maſters of that Family. Now that thoſe two Conſtitutions of theirs, have been ſufficiently broken, ſmall skil in Hiſtory, or in Converſation will demonſtrate.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their VVealth amaſſed, and that wrongfully too, as ſome of their own ſay, is a ſufficient Argument how well their <hi>Vow of Poverty</hi> is obſerved; for as the Prefacer to the <hi>Moral. Practice of the</hi> Jeſuites, ſpeaks, <hi>There is not any Artifice, Injuſtice, or Violence they imploy not to enrich themſelves, by the ſpoils of all ſorts of perſons, Secular and Religious; Soveraign and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate.</hi> And while after, <hi>Nothing eſcapes the claws of their Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. All <hi>England</hi> knows, as well as other Countries, how far they have complyed with that Rule of their own making, <hi>That none of them ſhould immix themſelves with the Secular buſineſs of Princes:</hi> for who greater Intermeddlers in State matters, than they? <hi>Hinc illae lachrymae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. The <hi>Practices</hi> and <hi>Methods,</hi> which the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have <hi>committed</hi> and <hi>uſed</hi> both <hi>here</hi> and in <hi>other Countries,</hi> have been the <hi>overthrow</hi> of other <hi>Religious</hi> of their own <hi>Church,</hi> and how then can <hi>they</hi> themſelves expect better <hi>Quarter?</hi> It is clearly prov'd <hi>againſt</hi> them here in <hi>England,</hi> that they have endeavour'd to <hi>deſtroy</hi> His <hi>Majeſtie's perſon</hi> by a <hi>violent</hi> death: Now there was formerly an <hi>order</hi> of the <hi>Humiliati</hi> in the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and they had divers <hi>Convents</hi> ſpread over <hi>Italy;</hi> they were to <hi>ſpend</hi> their time in <hi>ſtrict</hi> Exerciſes of <hi>Piety,</hi> and of <hi>ſelfe-abaſements,</hi> (as the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> pretend,) whence they had their <hi>Name.</hi> But, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof, growing <hi>looſe</hi> and <hi>wanton,</hi> and <hi>ſwerving</hi> from their <hi>firſt Auſterity,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Borrhomeo,</hi> a <hi>grave Prelate,</hi> undertook to be their <hi>Protector</hi> and <hi>Reformer</hi> both, who entering upon his <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Reformation,</hi> did ſo <hi>curb</hi> their <hi>licentious Wickedneſſes,</hi> that <hi>ſome</hi> of them <hi>conſpired</hi> to take away his <hi>life,</hi> which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly was <hi>attempted</hi> by them, whiles he was at his <hi>Prayers,</hi> by the diſcharge of a <hi>Piſtol;</hi> (was not the like <hi>Method</hi> of <hi>Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> deſigned againſt <hi>our King?</hi>) which by <hi>Gods</hi> providence did <hi>pierce</hi> his <hi>garments,</hi> and not <hi>wound</hi> his Body, to the <hi>hazard</hi> of his <hi>life.</hi> This <hi>Fact</hi> did ſo inrage Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fifth then ſitting, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97685:14"/>
he ſent out a <hi>Bull</hi> for the utter <hi>extirpation</hi> of that <hi>whole Order,</hi> notwithſtanding the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Interceſſion to the contrary, <hi>Anno</hi> 1577. which <hi>Bull</hi> is recited <hi>verbatim</hi> in <hi>Toſcanus</hi> his Book entituled, <hi>Summa conſtitutionum &amp; rerum in Eccleſiâ Romana ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarum à Gregorio Nono uſque ad Sixtum Quintum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If an Attempt upon a ſingle Cardinal can work the diſſolution of an whole Order, what ſhall thoſe many Attempts upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Princes do, ſome having been actually murdered, others de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to the ſlaughter by the Council and Contrivances of the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> certainly their Caſe equals, if not exceeds that of the <hi>Humiliati:</hi> Wherefore let them look to themſelves; for when <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes are incenſed, the ſtorm muſt light ſomewhere, and why not on the moſt guilty? Neither can the Pope himſelf, in ſuch Circumſtances, ſecure their Intereſt (no more then <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth could prevail upon the <hi>Venetian,</hi> to hinder their Non-excluſion from that City.) For to ſave himſelf and his Conclave, he will doubtleſs ſacrifice any particular Order of <hi>Religious</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
               <p>I know the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> doth labour to elude that Inſtance, by alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diſparity of Caſes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Say they, 'twas not one, or two ſingle perſons that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt Cardinal <hi>Barrhomeo,</hi> but the whole Order of the <hi>Humiliati</hi> in general, and therefore the Guilt being diffuſed over all the whole <hi>Sodalty,</hi> was juſtly ſuppreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They prevaricate in this Allegation; for there were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Convents of that Order ſpread over <hi>Italy,</hi> who cannot be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed ſo much as to have known any thing of that particular Fact, till after the <hi>Notoriety</hi> thereof by the Event: So that it was the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt only of a few particular Members, which redounded to the prejudice and overthrow of their whole Body; for when the minds of Rulers are exaſperated againſt any Society of men, for the Enormities of ſome few of their number, then that ſaying of <hi>Tacitus</hi> takes place, <hi>Habet aliquid ex iniquo omne magnum exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum, quod in ſingulos utilitate publicâ rependitur.</hi> Yet I am apt to think, that if the whole Body of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> could be put to the Teſt, there are very few of them, of any conſideration, which did not know and approve the late Bloody Deſigns againſt <hi>England,</hi> though few of the Actors therein, in compariſon, have been called forth to ſuffer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It was the viciouſneſs of their lives, ſay they, which was the cauſe of their diſſolution, and not their Attempt againſt the <hi>Cardinal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Bull</hi> it ſelf ſpeaks to the contrary, where, although the looſeneſs of their lives be inſtanced in, yet all is ſumm'd up into that Bloody Undertaking againſt their Patron, grounded on their Impenitency and Hatred of the Inſtrument of their Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. I judge, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are as much concerned, to be reproved, regulated, and reformed by Princes, or Prelates, as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97685:14"/>
any of the <hi>Humiliati,</hi> unleſs perhaps they diſguiſe themſelves more, and work more under ground in their Contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. In Scripture Deciſion, <hi>Pride goeth before Deſtruction, and a haughty look before a fall.</hi> This Increpation will much concern that Order of men, if we may believe many Writers of their own Church: For who more aſpiring? Who more ſuperci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious, than they? VVho greater undervaluers and underminers of others, even of their own Religion. Neither are theſe faults ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to them by the Envy of a Contrariant, but they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by Members of the <hi>Roman Communion;</hi> if it were fit for me to enlarge the number of Quotations, I could cite ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Authors to this purpoſe; but I ſhall content my ſelf with one or two Inſtances. 1. In the year 1640. they printed a Book in <hi>Flanders,</hi> entituled, <hi>The Image of the firſt Age, of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Jeſus,</hi> wherein they repreſent all the differing Events, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening to their Society, ſince their eſtabliſhment in 1540. which they purſue with ſo much Affectation, Vanity, and Pride, that as the Prefacer to the <hi>Moral Practice of the</hi> Jeſuits doth ſpeak. <hi>We cannot open the Book without abhorring the Impudence of theſe Fathers, in turning all things to their advantage, and labouring to draw glory from that, which ought rather to humble and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. There is a Book written Originally in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue, by a Biſhop of that Nation, which contains an Apology for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Orders of Religion againſt the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> addreſſed to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Tenth, and printed at <hi>Conimbre,</hi> in the year 1654. called, <hi>The Theatre of</hi> Jeſuitiſm; which, if it were commonly to be had, it would ſo diſplay the Haughtineſs, Avarice, and other Enormities of that Order, that the time of their expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without Repentance, may be judged to be near at hand eſpecially conſidering,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. The high diſguſt they have raiſed againſt themſelves amongſt moſt of their other <hi>Eccleſiaſticks,</hi> which is a great <hi>Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtick</hi> of their fall. I have given an hint of this before; it is not to be queſtioned, but that other <hi>Religious</hi> Orders of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, were in being long before the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> were thought of, neither are they now ſo fond of them, but they can as eaſily part with their Society; for no man in his right wits would court that which is a prejudice and inconvenience to himſelf; yea that, which would labour to <hi>ſupplant</hi> and <hi>ruine</hi> him? This is the preſent <hi>caſe,</hi> the <hi>Seculars</hi> have been put to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and to evince their own uſefulneſs in the Church; that was the deſign of <hi>Watſon</hi>'s <hi>Quodlibets,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the aforementioned Book, called the <hi>Theatre of Jeſuitiſm;</hi> certainly then they look'd on the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> as their Supplanters and Underminers, ſo that unleſs they are willing to court their own diminution, yea, total Aboliſhment, they cannot have much
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97685:15"/>
reſpect for that Order: I ſay, <hi>total Aboliſhment,</hi> becauſe <hi>Parſons,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> in a Book publiſhed heretofore, entituled, <hi>The Reformation of</hi> England, concludes with this ſaying, <hi>That if</hi> England <hi>ever return to the</hi> Romiſh <hi>Religion, all Eccleſiaſtical E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates muſt be put in common, and the care of them committed to ſeven Sages of the Society of Jeſus, to diſtribute them as they ſhall think fit, and that no</hi> Fryer <hi>of any other Order, muſt be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to paſs into</hi> England, <hi>and the Pope himſelf, for five years at leaſt, muſt not preſent to any Benefice, but refer himſelf wholly to thoſe ſeven perſons of that Company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If that Project of his aſpiring mind had taken place, then farewell all <hi>Seculars</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> yea, and all other Orders of <hi>Regulars</hi> too, unleſs ſuch as would have turn'd Penſioners to the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and have truckled under them.</p>
               <p>To cloſe this <hi>Argument,</hi> he that ſhall conſider what is ſaid in the beginning of the Preface to the Book called, <hi>The Moral Practice of the</hi> Jeſuits, in theſe words, <q>There's do doubt, but all who love the purity of the Moral Doctrine of Chriſt are very ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the corruption the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> labour to introduce thereunto, by the Opinions they have invented; but it may be ſaid, That nothing is more dreadful in the Conduct of theſe Fathers, than to ſee them purſue thoſe corrupt Maximes in their practice, and that of the many things they allow in others contrary to the Law of God and the principles of the Goſpel, there is not any they commit not themſelves to ſatisfie their Avarice, or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Grandeur and Glory of their Society.</q> And a while after; <q>All the Catholick Univerſities, particularly thoſe of <hi>Cracovie, Lovanie,</hi> and <hi>Padua,</hi> thoſe of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> the Biſhops, the Clergy, all the Orders of Religion, and the Courts of Parliament almoſt every where, oppoſed their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment, as contrary to the good of the Church and the ſecurity of States.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, he that ſhall conſider theſe paſſages, will conclude that Order not to be very acceptable to that Church, of which they are Members; and conſequently that other Orders would be glad to rid their hands of them, if they knew how: Theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, made upon the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> have reach'd the hearts of ſome of their own Members; for though in that Book, which I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd before, call'd, <hi>The Image of the firſt Age,</hi> &amp;c. they crown themſelves with many glorious <hi>Epithets,</hi> diſcovering a ſelf-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, even to the <hi>Nauſeation</hi> of the ſober; yet <hi>Mariana,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Jeſuite, (he, who is moſt criminated for his <hi>King-killing</hi> Doctrines,) hath written an expreſs Treatiſe of the faults and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of their Society, <q>which (he ſays) was ſo much changed, that if <hi>Ignatius</hi> himſelf came again into the World, he would not know it.</q> And in <hi>ch.</hi> 14. he ſays, <q>That their Conduct is in ſome things capable to precipitate the Society into the Abyſs of deſtruction.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Hence alſo it was, that <hi>Mutius Vitteleſchi,</hi> their ſixth General,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97685:15"/>
reflecting upon that Criminal facility, wherewith thoſe of his Congregation embraced all the new Opinions, that tended (as his Phraſe is) to corrupt and ruin the Piety of the Faithful, ſays in a Letter addreſſed to the Superiors of all their Houſes, <hi>That there was reaſon to fear, the latitude and liberty of Opinion of ſome of the Society, eſpecially in the matter of Manners, would not only ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ruine the Company, but cauſe very great miſchiefs in the whole Church of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>impreſſions,</hi> which the matter of the <hi>former Arguments,</hi> or at leaſt ſome <hi>equivalent conſiderations,</hi> have made upon the <hi>two laſt</hi> mentioned <hi>Members</hi> of their <hi>Society</hi> (who doubtleſs had <hi>ſome</hi> more <hi>Partizans</hi> amongſt them, of the ſame <hi>ſentiment</hi>) is no good <hi>Omen</hi> of their <hi>long continuance:</hi> For as in an <hi>Army,</hi> if the <hi>Groſs</hi> thereof be routed, yet a particular <hi>Regiment</hi> or <hi>Brigade,</hi> if ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>cloſe</hi> and <hi>compact</hi> together, are with difficulty broken though charged in <hi>Front, Flank</hi> and <hi>Rear,</hi> but when once an <hi>Entrance</hi> is made in any part thereof, then all further <hi>reſiſtance</hi> is of no <hi>avail</hi> for their ſafety; ſo it hath been hitherto the <hi>great advantage</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> that he continues, in great part, <hi>intire,</hi> ſince his <hi>firſt erection,</hi> and hath not admitted of thoſe <hi>breaches, ſub-diviſions</hi> and <hi>reforms,</hi> which other <hi>Orders</hi> have, for the <hi>Benedictines</hi> have been <hi>reformed</hi> into <hi>Cluniacks, Ciſtertians,</hi> &amp;c. to their diminution and loſs; ſuch <hi>ſub-alter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> purgations</hi> do carry more than a Tacit intimation of <hi>ill humours, errors</hi> and <hi>defects,</hi> which the <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuitical Order</hi> by no means will admit; Tis true, <hi>Sabelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> tells us, <hi>That about the year</hi> 1366. <hi>there was an Order of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious at</hi> Siena <hi>in</hi> Italy, <hi>called Jeſuati, but the Hiſtorian deſtribes theſe to have been a fort of Lay Hermits, which wrought for their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and not being in Eccleſiaſtical Orders, did celebrate no Maſs, but ſpending their time in Prayer, and often repeating the Name of Jeſus, had thence their denomination;</hi> I do not find any continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this <hi>Order,</hi> though probably the <hi>Ignatian Jeſuit</hi> might from them borrow his <hi>Title,</hi> with ſome ſmall variation, but their appearance in the World was <hi>many years</hi> before the <hi>Ignatian Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> as now eſtabliſhed, did peep abroad; ſo this doth not <hi>affect</hi> the Loyoliſts.</p>
               <p>Of <hi>late years</hi> indeed, there hath been a <hi>deſign</hi> to <hi>ſuperſete</hi> a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male <hi>Engliſh Order,</hi> under the Name of <hi>Jeſuiteſſes;</hi> and as the <hi>firſt Preacher</hi> of the <hi>actual Reſurrection</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was a <hi>Mary,</hi> ſo (they ſay) that the <hi>firſt</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuiteſſes</hi> had the ſame <hi>Name;</hi> but upon ſerious conſideration of their <hi>graver Eccleſiaſticks,</hi> the <hi>Iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraries</hi> of the Men, and the <hi>Lady Errantrys</hi> of the <hi>Women,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared together, <hi>being</hi> likely to have more of the <hi>Romance</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the <hi>Evangely</hi> therein, I do not find it did ſucceed. So that the preſent <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Ignatius</hi> remains intire without any ſucceeding alteration, as to their <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> more than what was allowed unto them by the <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ts</hi> of <hi>Paul</hi> the third, and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the third their <hi>Eſtabliſhers;</hi> and indeed there was <hi>Liberty</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:97685:16"/>
enough granted them by thoſe <hi>two Bulls;</hi> for thereby they had power to <hi>alter</hi> their <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> as they pleaſed, ſo that <hi>Pope Paul</hi> the third might ſeem to <hi>evacuate</hi> his <hi>own Grant,</hi> and inſtead of preſcribing <hi>Rules</hi> to them for <hi>their Government,</hi> by the <hi>latitude</hi> allowed they might <hi>change</hi> and <hi>caſt</hi> of his, and ſo govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as they pleaſed, for the words in the <hi>Bull,</hi> Engliſhed, are, <hi>That they may make particular Ordinances, which they ſhall judg fit for the Society, to the glory of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the profit of their Neighbours; And ſuch as are already made, or ſhall be made hereafter, they may change, alter or aboliſh according to the variety of place, time, and occaſion, and inſtead of them, make new. The which ſo changed, revoked, or new made, we will that they be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the foreſaid Authority of the Apoſtolick See, And by the ſame Authority of our ſpecial Grace and Favour we confirm them.</hi> Well then, the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> in reſpect of his <hi>Order</hi> remains <hi>unbroken,</hi> let us now ſee, how he carrys himſelf <hi>within doors,</hi> if no <hi>errors</hi> or <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages</hi> there, then ſurely there appear no <hi>ſymptoms</hi> of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. But if the contrary be manifeſt, then it may ſerve as a <hi>ſixth Argument,</hi> That their <hi>Order,</hi> unleſs <hi>reformed,</hi> is not long-liv'd.</p>
               <p>Let us hear then what opinion <hi>Melchior Canus, Biſhop</hi> of the <hi>Canaries,</hi> had of this <hi>Order;</hi> when he heard of the firſt <hi>appearance</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> he believed that the end of the <hi>World</hi> did draw nigh, and that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> would forthwith appear, for that his <hi>Fore-runners</hi> and <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> (ſo he called the <hi>Ignatians</hi>) began to walk abroad;</p>
               <p>But if <hi>he</hi> be excepted againſt by them, as a <hi>partial Author,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a <hi>Dominican,</hi> let us call in their own <hi>Mariana</hi> again, for he tells us in his fore-cited <hi>fourteenth Chapter, That if any one have but boldneſs enough, what fault ſo ever he be guilty of, he remains in the Society, if he have but the wit to frame an excuſe, or any pretence for what he hath committed; I paſs by</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>groſs Crimes, a great number whereof is winked at under colour of want of ſufficient proof, or fear to have them noiſed, and ſo become publick; for our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeems to aim at nothing elſe, but covering of Faults, like them that rake the Aſhes uppermoſt, as if the Fire, that lyes under, would not ſooner or later ſend forth ſome ſmoak,</hi> &amp;c. And a while after, <hi>A Provincial or Rector ſhall turn all upſide down, violate the Rules and Conſtitutions of the Order, ſquander away the Eſtate belonging to their Houſes, or give them to his Kinred, without any puniſhment after ſeveral years miſcarriage, but the rendring his condition bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than ever by diſcharging him of his Office; does any man know a Superiour chaſtiſed for ſuch exceſſes, as theſe?</hi> And afterwards, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us the Good are afflicted, yea put to Death, and the Wicked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, becauſe they are feared.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee, by the judgment of one of their own, Evils and Miſcarriages do abound amongſt them. The impreſſion then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97685:16"/>
made upon their Body, they may well fear a Total rout. And indeed the reſt of the Fraternity, are ſo incenſed againſt this <hi>Spaniard,</hi> for expoſing them ſo much, that they more freely except againſt (and ſeem to condemn) the King-killing Doctrines in him, then in any other Jeſuit; Yea Mr. <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van,</hi> lately executed, in his dying Speech did (though miſtakingly) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute that Doctrine unto him alone, of all their Sodality: The Core of the Matter lay in <hi>Mariana</hi>'s free increpation of their other Evils, which gave them occaſion to recriminate his opinion in that wherein they might moſt plauſibly except againſt him; and this may probably be the reaſon, why (as I ſaid before) the Jeſuits turned Advocates for the Order of the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliati;</hi> and would caſt the intended murder of Cardinal <hi>Borrhomeo,</hi> only upon two or three of them, becauſe that Cardinal was no Friend of theirs, and againſt whom they had a picque, becauſe he had baniſhed their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der out of <hi>Millain,</hi> where he was Archbiſhop, and preferred Seculars in their rooms.</p>
               <p>Let us hear what <hi>Watſon</hi> ſays in this matter, <hi>This good Cardinal</hi> (ſays he) ſpeaking of Cardinal <hi>Borromeus, whoſe rare Virtues all</hi> Europe <hi>talked of, obſerving well the pride of the Jeſuits, their practices for inriching, advancing, and bringing of themſelves to be admired of all men,</hi> Lucifer <hi>like, and their Cony-catching devices for the alluring of the freſh-wits, Chrildren of moſt toward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and thoſe of rareſt aſpects, and great of hopes, having intelligence how they held the like courſe and ſtate, under colour of teaching and bringing up of Youth, in the Dutchy of</hi> Millain, <hi>he thought them no fit men to remain within his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction; whereupon he baniſh'd them out of all thoſe places, eſteeming it far more neceſſary to have ſuch apt men, and thoſe of the fineſt wits, quickeſt ſpirits, and likeliſt to prove great Clerks, to become ſecular Prieſts, as thoſe appointed by inſtitution divine to take upon them the care of Souls; This he prudently conceited was more convenient, and the bounden duty of them, that were indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent what ſtate of Life they took them unto in the Church of God, rather to have them Secular Prieſts, than intruded into any other Order of Religion or Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Life whatſoever, which intermedleth not</hi> ex profeſſo <hi>with any ſuch Charge, but live after the preſcript Rules of their Orders, private to themſelves, as their Vow and Profeſſion bind all them to.</hi> Thus he, and the ſame <hi>Watſon,</hi> makes it one Article in his fifth <hi>Quodlibet, Whether the Jeſuits, or the Seminary Seculars, be fitter for Government</hi> in the Engliſh Colledges beyond the Seas, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the two is more neceſſary, either reſpecting Gods Church, or the Weal of our Country <hi>(England)</hi> to have the bringing up of Engliſh Youths there? Which queſtion he reſolves on the part of the Seculars.</p>
               <p>And indeed, the Education of Youth is one of the prime Artifices of the <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> whereby he labours to advance himſelf, and depretiate other <hi>Orders</hi> of <hi>Religion.</hi> For this young <hi>Fry</hi> is, as it were, the <hi>Nurſery</hi> of their <hi>Society,</hi> which they ſtudy earneſtly to maintain. And indeed, in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Inſtitution of youths into their <hi>Colledges,</hi> they uſe a great deal of exactneſs and care; for the <hi>Rectors</hi> uſually inform themſelves of the Parentage, of the Eſtate, or hope and proſpect thereof; of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Complexions, Diſpoſitions, and Genius, of their promptneſs of wit, of the proficiency in Learning, in their Novitiates and Scholars; all which they enter in their <hi>Adverſaria,</hi> or <hi>Leiger-Books,</hi> (like good Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptants) in diſtinct Columns; and they make this uſe of theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Enquiries, that they may apply ſutable Baits to engage their <hi>Novices</hi> to the love of their <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> beyond any other ſort of <hi>Religions;</hi> ſo that if any ſhould admire how ſo many able and learned men, and ſuch great Writers (as <hi>Alegambe</hi> hath reckoned them up in his Book called <hi>Bibliotheca Societatis</hi>) ſhould as it were dote upon this Order, and eſteem it their priviledge and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97685:17"/>
honour to be cooptated or admitted thereunto. It doth much abate our wonder, when we conſider the Philtre of Education, and the <hi>principles</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into them at their firſt admiſſion, with the charming and ingratiating Allurements, uſed to them afterwards, eſpecially if noble, rich, and wealthy: It is reported of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that when they grow up, they love their Nurſes, and <hi>Foſter-Fathers,</hi> better than their own natural Parents, —<hi>a Teneris aſſueſcere multum eſt,</hi> ſays the Poet, herein the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> reſembles them, continuing to be ſo highly affected with his <hi>Gremial</hi> and <hi>Nutritious Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe who do more ſtrictly <hi>Anatomize</hi> this Order of <hi>Men,</hi> do divide them principally into <hi>three Ranks;</hi> the knowledge of the diviſion will not be unuſeful to <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. There are ſome Gentlemen, ordinarily of good houſes, and fair Eſtates, who live wholly after a <hi>Secular way,</hi> as <hi>Lay-Brethren</hi> of the <hi>Society;</hi> they are not actually obliged to the obſervation of the <hi>Rules</hi> of their <hi>Order,</hi> but enter into a <hi>Vow,</hi> to put on the <hi>Habit,</hi> when it ſhall pleaſe the <hi>Father-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> to command them; and therefore theſe are called, <hi>Jeſuits in voto;</hi> of ſuch they make mighty advantage, in order to the ſetting up of their <hi>Monarchy,</hi> or rather <hi>Pambaſileia,</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Dominion</hi> over all other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. For ſome of this Claſs are uſually maintained in the Palaces of all great Princes, and in the houſes of Noble men, who by the Mediation of their Adherents, are many times induced into the Prince's or Noble-man's ſervice, as Counſellours, Secretary, or the like; theſe again perſwade that Prince or Great-man reſpectively to take ſome actual <hi>Jeſuite</hi> for his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor or Chaplain; and by this means the <hi>ſecret Conſultations</hi> of Princes are diſcover'd, and their Deſigns prevented; and yet things are ſo cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carryed, that no man can faſten on the true Author, but it commonly happens, that the <hi>greateſt ſuſpicion</hi> lyes on the moſt innocent. Thus an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of their own Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond ſort is of thoſe who are actually reſident in their <hi>Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> and <hi>Colledges,</hi> as Prieſts, Clerks, or Converts, who of themſelves have no power to leave the <hi>Order,</hi> but at the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of <hi>their General</hi> and <hi>Superiours</hi> may be diſpenſed with; theſe are moſtly buſyed in the <hi>Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes</hi> of thoſe <hi>Colledges</hi> to which they relate.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third rank is of thoſe who are mainly given up to Policy, for the aggrandizing of their <hi>Society,</hi> and enlarging the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Priviledges thereof;</hi> theſe are not always choſen out of the moſt deſerving and beſt learned of their Society, but out of the moſt confident, bold, or daring, as moſt likely to ſerve their end, by inſinuating themſelves into the <hi>Affairs</hi> and <hi>Councils</hi> of <hi>Secular Princes,</hi> that from thence they may fiſh out what is contributary to <hi>their Deſigns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt and laſt ſort are thoſe who are chiefly excepted againſt, and to whom <hi>Claudius Aquaria,</hi> one of their own <hi>Generals,</hi> did formerly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute two great Evils, which he calls <hi>Secularity</hi> and <hi>Auliciſm:</hi> The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was this, Their ſaid <hi>General</hi> having obſerved (as well as <hi>Mariana</hi>) the <hi>Defects</hi> and <hi>Errours</hi> in their <hi>Government,</hi> wrote a Book, printed at <hi>Rome, A. D.</hi> 1615. wherein he lays open the Diſeaſes of the Society, and his Eſſays for the healing of them; take his Reproof in his own words. <hi>Saecularitas &amp; Auliciſmus inſinuans in familiaritates &amp; gratiam externorum, morbus eſt in Societate &amp; intra &amp; extra periculoſus, &amp; iſtis, qui eum patiuntur, &amp; nobis fere neſcientibus paulatim ſubintrat, ſpecie quidem lucrifaciendi Principes, Praelatos, Magnates, conciliandi ad Divinum obſequium hujuſmodi homines So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietati, juvandi proximos,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſed re vera quoerimus interdum nos ipſos, &amp; paulatim ad ſaecularia deflectimus. Secularity</hi> (ſays he) and <hi>Auliciſme</hi> inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97685:17"/>
into the acquaintance and favour of thoſe without, is a Diſeaſe in the Society, dangerous within and without, to thoſe who undergo and ſuffer it, and it creeps in upon us almoſt un-a-wares; the pretence is to gain Princes, Prelates, and Noble-men, to the eſteem of the Society, for the Service of God, and the good of our Neighbour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the truth is, we ſeek our ſelves, and by little and little revolt to a Secular Life.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Author</hi> in another <hi>Tract,</hi> intituled <hi>Inſtitutiones pro Superiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Societatis,</hi> publiſhed at <hi>Rome</hi> alſo the ſame time, further <hi>deſcribes</hi> that <hi>miſchief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſt &amp; alia malorum Radix longe periculoſiſſima, eo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> periculoſior, quo minus vulgo noxia conſeri ſolet, rerum, ſcilicet, externarum occupatio, in quam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periores ferri, ac variis nominibus ſupra modum effundi ſolent. Sunt enim qui naturae quadam propenſione ad diſtractiones proni, non ſolum oblatas occaſiones cupide arripiunt, ut operam ſuam impendant, ſed eas ipſimet ultro quaerunt, &amp; naſci quodammodo ac ſuccreſcere faciunt. Alii per ſpeciem proximos lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cri faciendi, multis ſeſe viſitationibus implicant, iiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> non modo non neceſſariis, ſed paerum etiam utilibus, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in his ita verſantur, ut a ſaecularium moribus parum abſcedant.</hi> The ſenſe is, That their <hi>mixing</hi> themſelves in <hi>ſecular affairs</hi> is a <hi>dangerous</hi> evil in their <hi>Society,</hi> of which their <hi>ſuperiours</hi> are much <hi>guilty,</hi> ſome of which being <hi>naturally</hi> prone to raiſe <hi>diſtractions,</hi> do not only greedily <hi>apprehend</hi> all <hi>occaſions</hi> offered to promote <hi>them,</hi> but alſo do their <hi>endeavour</hi> to <hi>create</hi> more <hi>opportunities</hi> to <hi>raiſe, foment,</hi> and Cheriſh them. Others entangle themſelves in many viſits (on pretence of gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their neighbours) needleſs, and unuſeful, and demean themſelves ſo therein, that they little or nothing differ in their manners from Seculars.</p>
               <p>The cure which he preſcribes for the healing of this diſeaſe, which I wiſh all of the Society would obſerve the method of, is, <hi>Inſtruct.</hi> 14. <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Praecidantur initio iſtae familiaritates cum Principibus, ante quam adoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant &amp; radices agant, quae ſocietati noſtrae, niſi fortiter obſiſtamus, graviter minitantur, praefertim cum ſuperiores connivent,</hi> (i.) Let all thoſe familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities with Princes be diſcarded at the beginning, before they be ſetled or take root, which threaten a great miſchief to our Society, unleſs we ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſiſt, eſpecially our Superiours winking at it.</p>
               <p>It ſeems this General was more ſober and honeſt than the reſt of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors; or elſe the cenſure of their <hi>Mariana</hi> aforementioned was ill grounded (which we can hardly imagine) for he having in one Chapter laid to the charge of their Society, <hi>That in diſtributing of rewards and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments,</hi> there was more equity amongſt Thieves and Robbers, than amongſt them. And moreover that Vertue and Learning in their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dality were rather an hindrance to preferment than a ſtep thereunto: In his 10th <hi>Chap.</hi> of the Regiment of the Society, he imputes the cauſe of theſe evils to the Ambition, Pride, and Arbitrarineſs of their Generals. I ſhall repeat his own words, <hi>Pervenimus nunc ad fontem &amp; Originem noſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum turbarum ac moleſtiarum, quas in Societate experimur ſingularis ferus depaſtus eſt eam. Monarchia ista, meâ ſententiâ, nos humi affligit ac pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternit, non quia ſit Monarchia, ſed quia non ſit bene temperata: Haec enim bellua eſt, quae quicquid attigit, populatur ac vaſtat quam niſi vinculis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcamus, non eſt, quod ullam nobis quietem polliceamur,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Et ſi leges ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus, eaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> plures numero, quam neceſſe eſt, Generalis tamen nihil in Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernatione leges moratur, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in dandis officiis, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> admittendo ſocios ad profeſſionem, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in Conſtituendis Collegiis, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> innumeris in rebus aliis. Nam ſi leges ſint, ille in omnibus, aut prope in omnibus diſpenſandi ac legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quem libeat ſolvendi auctoritate utitur.</hi> (i.) We are now come to the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97685:18"/>
and Fountain of all the Troubles, which we experiment in our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, One ſingle Ravager hath eat it quite up. Our Monarchy, in my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion doth quite overthrow us, not becauſe it is a Monarchy, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not well tempered. This is the Beaſt, which waſtes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it lights upon, and unleſs we fetter and reſtrain it, we can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe our ſelves no reſt, &amp;c. It is true, we have Laws, and thoſe more than enough, yet our General regards them not at all, in his Government, neither in beſtowing of Offices, nor in admitting Fellows to the Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor in Conſtituting of Colleges, nor in many other things; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we have Laws, yet he, almoſt in all things, uſeth his Authority to diſpenſe with the Laws, as he pleaſeth. And a little after to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
               <p>Thus Our Monarchical General, with a Provincial, and two or three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidents, to the grief of others more deſerving, do govern all things in every Province at their Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>To draw towards a Concluſion, 'Tis no acceptable work to me to dive into the evils of men; or to pore ſo intently on their defects, as to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look what good may be in them. The worſe I wiſh to all, is Repentance and Amendment of life; Nevertheleſs, if I ſhould enumerate all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Miſcarriages, Injuries, Frauds, Impoſtures, Obſcenities, Treaſons, and other Villanies imputed to this Order of Men, by Members of their own (Church, many of them circumſtantiated as to time, place, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) I ſhould ſwell my Tract a little too much: I know the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have replyed to ſome of thoſe Accuſations, and that, in moſt things, leanly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, for when the punctuality of Time and Place is given in Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, upon unqueſtionable credit, 'tis beyond the Effrontery of humane Nature, to expect credit upon a bare denyal. He who deſires to know more of theſe Men, Let him read the Provincial's Letters, otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the <hi>Myſtery of Jeſuitiſme,</hi> with a Second part thereof, called, <hi>A fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcovery of the Myſtery of Jeſuitiſme;</hi> Let him alſo conſult thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two Books, one called, <hi>The Jeſuits Morals,</hi> Tranſlated by Dr. <hi>Tongue;</hi> The other Entituled, <hi>The Moral Practiſe of the Jeſuits,</hi> compoſed by the Doctors of the <hi>Sorbon;</hi> And then no doubt, he will receive ample ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
               <p>I ſhall cloſe all with the Abridgment of one pleaſant ſtory, taken out of the laſt mentioned Book. It is this, A <hi>Smith</hi> at <hi>Madrid</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> placed his Son amongſt the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> there, giving them for his reception, the ſum of 2000 Ducats, (for entertainments, you muſt know, are very dear, ſo near the Court.) The young man being admitted, was a while after ſtrip'd of his habit, and returned home, but the Money refuſed to be repai'd; The <hi>Smith</hi> ſues them at the Law, They by favour obtain ſentence againſt him; The poor man betook himſelf to his ſhifts, and reſolved, becauſe his Sons habit had coſt him ſo much, he would ſo order the matter, that it ſhould regain him part of his Money: Whereupon cloathing his Son in the Garb of a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> he made him work daily at his Anvil, the quick-ſented Fathers, having notice of it, leſt their Cheat ſhould be publickly known amongſt the Common people, immediately ſent for the <hi>Smith,</hi> paid him his Mony, and redeemed their Habit from a Mock-ſhew: But if they could have bought ſilence, as well as the Robe and Hood, This ſtory doubtleſs had never come to our Ears.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
